{"tossups": [{"question": "This settlement was abandoned after the loss of a trade network centered on Kilwa, leading its inhabitants to settle Mutapa. Sites at this settlement include the Great Enclosure and the Hill Complex, where eight birds carved of soapstone were once supposed to have stood. It was constructed by the Shona people, who protected themselves with high walls built without mortar. For ten points, name this Iron Age settlement that lends its name to an African country with capital Harare.", "answer": "<b> Great Zimbabwe</b> (prompt on Zimbabwe)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was not given songwriting credit on \u201cNever Learn Not to Love\u201d by the Beach Boys, even though it was derived from this man\u2019s song \u201cCease to Exist.\u201d This man\u2019s belief in hidden messages on the Beatles\u2019<em> White Album</em> inspired the idea of a \u201cHelter Skelter\u201d race war. One of the stars of<em> Valley of the</em> <em>Dolls</em>, Sharon Tate, was over eight months pregnant when this man\u2019s followers murdered her in 1969. For ten points, name this cult leader who died in prison in 2017.", "answer": "Charles<b> Manson</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A treaty with this name included the secret Act of Seclusion, by which the future William III lost the title of Stadtholder. The first and third Anglo-Dutch Wars were ended by treaties of this name. A 1931 statute of this name established protocols between the U.K. and dominion realms. A religious building with this name was built on the orders of Edward the Confessor and was the site of his burial. For ten points, give the name shared by the abbey where British monarchs are coronated.", "answer": "<b> Westminster</b> (accept Treaty of<b> Westminster</b>; accept Statute of<b> Westminster</b>; accept <b>Westminster</b> Abbey)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One of these ships was deemed too slow for the Pacific Theatre and was used in Operation Leader in Norway. During Operation Torch, one of these ships supported ground troops and was named<em> Ranger</em>. In order to prevent the capture of Port Moresby by Japan, two of these ships were sent to the Coral Sea, leading to the scuttling of one called the<em> Lexington</em>. These ships were not present during the attack on Pearl Harbor. The<em> Yorktown</em> was, for ten points, what type of ship that provides a runway for warplanes?", "answer": "aircraft<b> carriers</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man publicly debated Michel Foucault [foo-koh] in a TV program titled<em> Human Nature: Justice</em> <em>versus Power</em>. This man defended the right of a Holocaust denier to publish in the Faurisson affair. This thinker, who worked with Edward Herman on a book critical of the Vietnam War, coined the nonsense phrase \u201ccolorless green ideas sleep furiously\u201d to illustrate the difference between grammar and syntax. For ten points, name this outspoken MIT professor, often considered the father of modern linguistics.", "answer": "(Avram) Noam<b> Chomsky</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "While serving this state, Matthew Lyon spat tobacco juice and defended himself with fireplace tongs during a 1798 incident with Roger Griswold in the House of Representatives. Seth Warner served as a captain in a militia sometimes called the Bennington Mob, named for a city in this state. Benning Wentworth made a series of land grants, including the town of Burlington, in, for ten points, what 14th US State where, in 1825, the Marquis de Lafayette toured Montpelier?", "answer": "<b> Vermont</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s brother killed Spencer Pettis after Pettis criticized this man\u2019s work. Louis McLane was reassigned to the State Department for refusing to remove funds from an organization run by this man. After Langdon Cheves resigned, James Monroe replaced him with this man. In a political cartoon, this man is shown wearing a top hat as part of a many-headed monster being slain by the seventh President of the United States. Andrew Jackson was challenged by, for ten points, what final president of the Second Bank of the United States?", "answer": "Nicholas<b> Biddle</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This artist included a depiction of Sappho holding a scroll with her name on it, as well as Dante, Boccacio, and the nine muses in a depiction of Mount Parnassus. This artist, who began his career under Perugino, included a self-portrait as the Greek painter Apelles in one of his four frescoes for the Stanza della Segnatura, commissioned by Pope Julius II. For ten points, name this Italian painter who painted Plato and Aristotle conversing in his<em> The School of Athens</em>.", "answer": "<b> Raphael</b> (accept either or both underlined parts of<b> Raffaello Sanzio</b> da Urbino)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician\u2019s attempt in mid-2017 to suppress the Maute [mao-tay] group led to a protracted siege of the city of Marawi. This man, who chaired the most recent ASEAN summit, attracted controversy in 2016 for comments surrounding the rape of the Australian missionary Jacqueline Hamill.<em> Time</em> Magazine labeled this man as \u201cThe Punisher\u201d in response to his use of extrajudicial \u201cdeath squads\u201d against drug dealers. For ten points, name this current president of the Philippines.", "answer": "Rodrigo Roa<b> Duterte</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A scandal involving illegal shipments of arms to this country involved Charles Pasqua, Jean-Christophe Mitterand, and several French writers and artists. The Bicesse Accord set up a plan for democracy in this country with the support of President Jos\u00b4e Eduardo dos Santos. In 1992, fighting in this country intensified in the Halloween Massacre between the ruling party once backed by Cuban military aid, the MPLA, and the opposition UNITA party. For ten points, name this former Portuguese colony that is governed from Luanda.", "answer": "<b> Angola</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1917, this state\u2019s governor, Frank Lowden, sent National Guardsmen to stop a race riot, but most Guardsmen refused to help while police joined the fighting; a 1917 Silent Protest Parade in New York City was a direct response to that riot in this state. The arrest of two black men in this state\u2019s capital sparked a 1908 race riot that led to the creation of the NAACP. For ten points, name this state where mass lynchings took place in East St. Louis and Springfield.", "answer": "<b> Illinois</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this state, Wesley Everest was lynched after the IWW and the American Legion clashed in the town of Centralia. Protesters in this state made pamphlets encouraging revolution with phrase \u201cRussia Did It\u201d during a 1919 general strike that was remarkably</b> <b>peaceful, yet put down with troops by Mayor Ole (+)</b> <b>Hanson. This state is home to</b> <b>the Hanford Works site, which was part of the Manhattan Project. During the Great Depression, workers built the (*)</b> Grand Coulee Dam on the Columbia River in, for ten points, what Pacific Northwest state where Boeing built World War II bombers in Seattle?", "answer": "<b> Washington</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A device that relies on this effect called an h/e apparatus can be used to experimentally determine Planck\u2019s constant. This effect was discovered after an observation that illumination with UV light made electrodes produce (+) sparks more easily. As the theories of relativity were still controversial in 1921, the Nobel committee emphasized the discovery of this effect in (*)</b> Albert Einstein\u2019s citation. For ten points, name this effect in which high-energy photons dislodge electrons from a metal.", "answer": "<b> photoelectric</b> effect", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s brief, post-war second term as mayor ended when Gerald Templer fired him for \u201claziness and incompetence.\u201d This politician aimed to pull the Zentrum \u201cout of the</b> <b>tower\u201d by uniting Protestants and Catholics in one party. The Miracle on the (+)</b> <b>Rhine</b> <b>was caused by this man\u2019s finance minister, Ludwig Erhard. This leader, who defeated rival Kurt Schumacher in a 1949 election, controversially suggested that (*) </b> Bonn, not Frankfurt, be made his provisional capital. For ten points, name this founder of the Christian Democratic Union, the first Chancellor of West Germany.", "answer": "Konrad<b> Adenauer</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This country arrested hundreds of \u201cSwing Kids,\u201d who preferred English language music. The opera</b><em><b> Jonny Strikes Up</b></em><b> by Ernst Krenek was criticized in a music exhibition in this</b> <b>country, which commissioned (+)</b> <b>Carl Orff to write incidental music for Shakespeare\u2019s</b> <em><b>Midsummer Night\u2019s Dream</b></em><b> to replace Felix (*)</b> Mendelssohn\u2019s work. Jazz and twelve-tone music were banned as \u201cdegenerate music\u201d by, for ten points, what country from which Arnold Schoenberg and other Jewish composers fled in the 1930s?", "answer": "Nazi<b> Germany</b> (accept the<b> Third Reich</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Robert Calef denounced this event in a work that contains the controversial \u201cNarrative of a Visit.\u201d John Alden escaped this event but returned after \u201cthe public had regained its use of (+) reason.\u201d William Phips created a Court of Oyer and Terminer headed by William Stoughton during this event. (*) </b> Cotton Mather defended his role in this event in his<em> Wonders of</em> <em>the Invisible World</em>. For ten points, name this 1692 to 1693 bit of mass hysteria in Massachusetts during which numerous girls were executed for allegedly using magic.", "answer": "<b> Salem Witch</b> Trials", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For ten points, give this British royal name, also shared by a king who feuded with Archbishop of Canterbury Thomas Becket.", "answer": "<b> Henry</b> (accept<b> Henry</b> I; accept<b> Henry</b> II; accept<b> Henry</b> III)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}